<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sergey Samsonau</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Sergey Samsonau</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Sergey Samsonau</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Experimental labs with computer simulations</title>
      <link>/post/exp-labs-with-simulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/exp-labs-with-simulations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While teaching laboratories for calculus-based Physics I figured out there is no teaching curriculum available which would combine actual experiments with computer (or also called numerical) simulations. So, I developed a sequence of 7 lab modules to implement exactly that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Science</title>
      <link>/post/2018-04-22-data-science-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-04-22-data-science-in-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I gather some examples of use of Data Scince in a traditional sciences: Physics, Chemistry, Biology, and others&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/projects/</guid>
      <description>Recent papers and preprints  Computer simulations combined with experiments for calculus-based Physics laboratory course. Sergey V. Samsonau. arXiv:1804.09264 [physics.ed-ph], April 2018. Link
 Integrating Science Through Authentic Research in Secondary Schools
E. Mohlhenrich, S. V. Samsonau, R. P. Spencer. IEEE Integrated STEM Education Conference, March 2018. Link
 Thyroid Hormone Status in Stroke and Transient Ischemic Attack Patients
Halinouskaya, N. V.; Samsonau, S. V.; Usava, N. N.; Smychek, V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>/teaching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/</guid>
      <description>Physics  Algebra-based Physics (college and high school) Calculus-based Physics (college and high school) Quantum Mechanics (high school) I did setup and now supervise a nanotechnology research laboratory at a high school A course of labs designed to develop student&amp;rsquo;s research skill was developed and will be described soon A course of labs combining numerical simulations with experiments which I developed is now availabe on arxiv.org. Link  Data Science  Data Science class I did introduce and teach at a high school I did organize and now supervise Data Science research laboratory at a high school  Data Science I Data Science I course is designed to teach students analyze data using R language, as well as how to present results of analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essentials of Data Science</title>
      <link>/post/essentials-of-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/essentials-of-data-science/</guid>
      <description>There is a lot of information on Data Science on Internet. On this page I summarize the most essential things you would need to know to start working on real projects. The rest you can figure out on the way. This page is intentionally short (relativelly).
Books  R for Data Science An Introduction to Statistical Learning Data Science for Business  Tools, Installation and updating  installr package</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Animation Overview</title>
      <link>/post/animation-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/animation-overview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A short review of some methods allowing to create animations in R is presented bellow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>