<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Science on Simplissimo</title>
    <link>/tags/data-science/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Science on Simplissimo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/data-science/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple comparison</title>
      <link>/post/multiple-comparison/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/multiple-comparison/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Let say you have a data set with many columns and you would like to see if there are is any statistically significant dependence between some of the parameters. Just write a script and find those with p &amp;lt; 0.05 - right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually no&amp;hellip; You are almost guarantied to have at least 5% of those columns to be statistically significantly correlated. This is known as a &amp;ldquo;multiple comparison&amp;rdquo; problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Science in Science</title>
      <link>/post/2018-04-22-data-science-in-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-04-22-data-science-in-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here I gather some examples of use of Data Scince in a traditional sciences: Physics, Chemistry, Biology, and others&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/projects/</guid>
      <description>Recent papers and preprints  Computer simulations combined with experiments for calculus-based Physics laboratory course. Sergey V. Samsonau. arXiv:1804.09264 [physics.ed-ph], April 2018. Link
 Integrating Science Through Authentic Research in Secondary Schools
E. Mohlhenrich, S. V. Samsonau, R. P. Spencer. IEEE Integrated STEM Education Conference, March 2018. Link
 Thyroid Hormone Status in Stroke and Transient Ischemic Attack Patients
Halinouskaya, N. V.; Samsonau, S. V.; Usava, N. N.; Smychek, V.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essentials of Data Science</title>
      <link>/post/essentials-of-data-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/essentials-of-data-science/</guid>
      <description>There is a lot of information on Data Science on Internet. On this page I summarize the most essential things you would need to know to start working on real projects. The rest you can figure out on the way. This page is intentionally short (relativelly).
Books  R for Data Science An Introduction to Statistical Learning Data Science for Business  Tools, Installation and updating  installr package</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>